Guide to the Barbara Wertheim Tuchman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1953-1969; Series II; 9.5 linear feet (24 Boxes, 4 Folios, 6 Card file boxes)
  - ARTICLES
    - "Perdicaris Alive or Raisuli Dead," American Heritage [1959], 1958-1961, 1968
      - Typescript, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 367)
      - Copy of magazine (Box 21, Folder 368)
    - "Why I became a Historian: reply to a query," National Library Week. Carbon, notes, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 369)
    - "Poker - A Game, Gentlemen, A Game," Esquire. Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 21, Folder 370)
    - Remarks on Kennedy Funeral, St. Louis Post-Dispatch. Copy of newspaper, 1963 November 26 (Box 21, Folder 371)
    - "Dorothy and Red," Book Week. Correspondence, 1963 (Box 21, Folder 372)
    - "Can History Be Served Up Hot?" New York Times
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 373)
      - Xerox copy of article, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 374)
    - "When Does History Happen?" Prose and Criticism. Correspondence, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 375)
    - Vogue Magazine. Correspondence, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 376)
    - "History By the Ounce," Harper's Magazine
      - Correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box 21, Folder 377)
      - Copy of published article, July, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 378)
    - "History Recreated: A Guide to the Future?"
      - Writer's World (Box 21, Folder 379)
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 379)
    - "The Historian As an Artist," The Writer's Handbook. Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 21, Folder 380)
    - "Israel: Land of Unlimited Possibilities," Saturday Evening Post [Original title: "Sprinklers of Eilat"]
      - Photos-Israel (Box 21, Folder 381)
      - Prints of Chagall Windows (Box 21, Folder 382)
      - Research materials: pamphlets, tour guides (Box 21, Folder 383)
        - Historical pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 384)
        - Hebrew University (Box 22, Folder 385)
        - Israel Today (Box 22, Folder 386)
        - Pamphlets on various aspects of Israel (Box 22, Folder 387)
        - Pamphlets on the Dead Sea Scrolls (Box 22, Folder 388)
        - Israel's Peace Offer to the Arab States, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 389)
        - Reprint by Abba Eban, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 390)
        - Reprint - National Water Project, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 391)
        - Reprint - Commission on International Affairs, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 392)
      - Reprints (Box 22, Folder 393)
      - Research materials: Government Annual Report, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 394)
      - Government press releases, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 395)
      - Research - newsclippings, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 396)
      - Trip itinerary, undated (Box 22, Folder 397)
      - Research notes (Box 22, Folder 398)
      - Handwritten draft (Box 23, Folder 399)
      - Preliminary typescript (Box 23, Folder 400)
      - Incomplete carbon, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 401)
      - Final typescript, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 402)
      - Suggested corrections for text, March, 1966 (Box 23, Folder 403)
      - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 23, Folder 404)
      - Copy of published article, January 14, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 405)
    - "How We Entered World War I," New York Times Magazine [Original title: "Old and New Illusions"]
      - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 23, Folder 406)
      - Research note cards (Box 23, Folder 407)
      - Fragments of notes (Box 23, Folder 408)
      - Handwritten draft (Box 23, Folder 409)
      - Typescript of early draft (Box 23, Folder 410)
      - Carbon of final draft (Box 23, Folder 411)
      - Copy of published article, March 5, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 412)
    - "A Generation Discovers Jerusalem," Washington Post
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 413)
      - Copy of newspaper, July 9, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 414)
    - "Israel's Swift Sword," Atlantic Monthly
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 415)
      - Research material - biography - Aluf Uzi/Narkiss (Box 23, Folder 416)
      - Research material - newsclippings, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 417)
      - Notebooks (Box 23, Folder 418)
      - "Jerusalem United" typescript (Box 23, Folder 419)
      - Photos, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 420)
      - Handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 421)
      - Preliminary handwritten drafts (Box 23, Folder 422)
      - Preliminary typescript (Box 23, Folder 423)
      - Typescript with corrections (Box 23, Folder 424)
      - Copy of published article, September, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 425)
    - "In the Wake of War," Atlantic Monthly
      - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 23, Folder 426)
      - Research material - map of Israel (Box 23, Folder 427)
      - Article, "The Lesson of Israel" by Peregrine Worsthorne, Atlas, August, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 428)
      - Research material - newsclippings (Box 23, Folder 429)
      - Handwritten research notes (Box 23, Folder 430)
      - Miscellaneous draft segments (Box 23, Folder 431)
      - Handwritten draft (Box 23, Folder 432)
      - Preliminary typescript (Box 23, Folder 433)
      - Carbon (Box 23, Folder 434)
      - Carbon with corrections (Box 23, Folder 435)
      - Copy of published article, November, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 436)
    - "The Victors Are Not Hated," Copy of article published in Israeli newspaper, November 7,1967 (Box 23, Folder 437)
    - "Prepare for a U.S. Defeat in Vietnam," Newsday and other newspapers. Correspondence, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 438)
    - ["U.S. in Vietnam: Untenable Position Boding Defeat"] Philadelphia Inquirer. Handwritten draft, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 439)
    - Newsclipping, March 10, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 440)
    - ["Vietnam: the Need to Alter Course"], Carbon (Box 23, Folder 441)
    - "For the Abolition of the Presidency," unpublished typescript, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 442)
    - "Conversation with Arabs", undated (Box 23, Folder 443)
    - "Czar Reed," American Heritage (Box 23, Folder 444)
    - Receipts and financial matter concerning articles (Box 23, Folder 445)
  - BROADCAST
    - Invitations to Learning; WCBS, 1963 (Box 24A, Folder 446)
  - LETTERS TO THE EDITOR-- New York Times
    - Regarding Vietnam, February 20, 1966 (Box 24A, Folder 447)
    - Regarding closing of libraries, April 27 (Box 24A, Folder 448)
    - Regarding McCarthy supporters -- third party, July 5 (Box 24A, Folder 449)
    - Regarding Israel problem, July 14 (Box 24A, Folder 450)
  - POEM
    - "To a Mouse"; poem and news clipping which prompted writing, 1958 (Box 24A, Folder 451)
  - REVIEWS
    - Bullitt, William C. and Sigmund Freud, Thomas Woodrow Wilson ("Can History Use Freud," Atlantic Monthly )
      - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 24A, Folder 452)
      - Research notes, 1967 (Box 24A, Folder 453)
      - Galley proofs of book (Box 24A, Folder 454)
      - Jacket cover and blurb for book (Box 24A, Folder 455)
      - Handwritten draft of review (Box 24A, Folder 456)
      - Typescript of review (Box 24A, Folder 457)
      - Copy of published article (Box 24A, Folder 458)
    - Goodspeed, D.J., Ludendorff. Carbon of typescript (Box 24A, Folder 459)
    - Hausner, Gideon, Justice in Jerusalem ("Albatross Around Our Neck," New York Times Book Review )
      - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 24A, Folder 460)
      - Handwritten draft, undated (Box 24A, Folder 461)
      - Uncut version, 1966 (Box 24A, Folder 462)
    - Horne, Alistair, The Fall of Paris, New York Times Book Review, January, 1966 (Box 24A, Folder 463)
    - Liddell-Hart, Basil H., Memoirs ("The Mind Behind the Blitzkrieg," The Reporter ). Copy of published review, February 24, 1966 (Box 24A, Folder 464)
    - Watt, Richard M., Dare Call It Treason. Typescript (Box 24A, Folder 465)
    - Wighton, Charles and Gunter Peis, Hitler's Spies and Saboteur s. Typescript, 1958 (Box 24A, Folder 466)
  - SPEECHES
    - Address before American Library Association, July, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 467)
    - Address before Choate Club; correspondence, 1967 (Box 24B, Folder 468)
    - Address before Magazine Publisher's Association, March, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 269)
    - Address before Publisher's Ad Club, February 6, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 470)
    - "Belligerent Will in the 20th Century," Hebrew University; typescript, March, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 471)
    - "Book and Author," Washington Post, February 13, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 472)
    - Brearley; notes, May 30, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 473)
    - Dedication - Cos Cob Fire Company; program, 1957 (Box 24B, Folder 474)
    - Discussion of writing for a reader; Brearley, May 17, 1962 (Box 24B, Folder 475)
    - Revision of "Guide to the Future"; incomplete, undated (Box 24B, Folder 476)
    - "Historical Clues to Present Discontents," Pomona College, January, 1969 (Box 24B, Folder 477)
    - "The Historian as Creative Writer", undated (Box 24B, Folder 478)
    - "The Historian's Opportunity," American Historical Association
      - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 24B, Folder 479)
      - Research material
        - List of Book-of-the-Month-Club selections, 1926-1966 (Box 24B, Folder 480)
        - Literary Guild selections, 1955-1966 (Box 24B, Folder 481)
        - Best Seller Lists - Publisher's Weekly, 1945-1965 (Box 24B, Folder 482)
        - Publisher's Weekly, January, 1965 (Box 24B, Folder 483)
        - Pulitzer Prize winners, 1955-1965 (Box 24B, Folder 484)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 485)
      - Research notes, undated (Box 24B, Folder 486)
      - Preliminary draft, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 487)
      - Handwritten draft (Box 24B, Folder 488)
      - Typescript with corrections (Box 24B, Folder 489)
      - Typescript, December, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 490)
      - Saturday Review; copy of published article, February 25, 1967 (Box 24B, Folder 491)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 24B, Folder 492)
    - "History Without Fiction", undated (Box 24B, Folder 493)
    - Correspondence concerning lectures at Hebrew University, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 494)
    - "Historiography of World War I," Hebrew University. Lecture notes, March, 1966 (Box 24B, Folder 495)
    - "In Search of History" (Box 24B, Folder 496)
      - Greenwich Library, November 27, 1962 (Box 24B, Folder 496)
      - Phi Beta Kappa Address, Radcliffe
        - Correspondence, March 25, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 497)
        - Xerox copy of address published in Radcliffe Quarterly, 1963 (Box 24B, Folder 497)
    - "Is History a Guide to the Future?", October, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 501)
    - Israel rally speech; typescript, correspondence, newscli-pings, May-June, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 502)
    - "Jerusalem," Hebrew University; typescript, December, 1966 (Box 25, Folder 503)
    - "McCarthy's East," Hartford, Connecticut, 1968 (Box 25, Folder 504)
    - "The Missing Element," New York State Education (May, 1967); correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 25, Folder 505)
      - National Conference on Higher Education; typescript for publication, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 506)
      - Published article, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 507)
      - Publicity material for article (Box 25, Folder 508)
      - Two news clippings, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 509)
    - "On Writing History," Swarthmore, November 11, 1962 (Box 25, Folder 510)
    - "Open Mind", December 5, 1962 (Box 25, Folder 511)
    - "Oral History," delivered before several groups, 1968-1969 (Box 25, Folder 512)
    - "Pugnacity and Misery in History," Yale University, November, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 513)
    - Stimson Lecture at Goucher College, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 514)
    - "The View from the Thirties," Radcliffe Commencement address
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 515)
      - Handwritten draft (Box 25, Folder 516)
      - Notes, typescript, April, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 517)
      - Text release for press, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 518)
      - Published article, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 519)
      - Newsclippings, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 520)
    - "Writers and Readers," New York Literary Club, April 16, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 521)
  - Tuchman, Barbara W. Printed Proof of Stilwell's Try. New York, 1 Vol., 1971 (Box 26)
- Additional Material, 1951-[1967-1973]; Accession 1979-M-007; 4 linear feet (4 Paige boxes)
  Preliminary listing by Kathy Straka 5/17/79
  - Correspondence file concerning Stilwell including: Col. David D. Barrett; Frank Dorn; John K. Fairbank, 1951, 1967-1973 (Box 27)
  - Stilwell's diaries, typescript copies, 1900-1948 (Box 27)
  - Stilwell's speeches and lectures, typescript copies, 1927-1946, undated (Box 27)
  - Stilwell's letters, typescript copies, 1937-1938, undated (Box 27)
  - Note cards for Stilwell (4 boxes), undated (Box 28)
  - Stilwell, manuscript and first typed draft (3 document files) (Box 29)
  - Folder of notes, and hand drawn map of India and Burma, exhibit catalogue of newly elected members, American Academy of Arts and Letters 1972 (Box 29)
  - Map of Burma campaign (Box 29A)
  - Stilwell, typescript with corrections: Acknowledgement, Forward, Prologue, Chapters 1-10, 12-20, bibliography, reference sources, bibliographical note cards and notebook [1971], photographs, illustrations, maps and clippings file (Box 30)
- Additional Material, 1930, 1957-(1972-1979); Accession 1980-M-005; 1.5 linear feet (1 Paige box, 1 archive box)
  Received from Barbara Tuchman
  - Correspondence
    General note
    Select correspondence, together with correspondence and printed matter or organizations to which BT belongs or contributes, correspondence and clippings concerning awards, and some fan mail. There is little personal correspondence, and for the most part BT has not kept copies of her replies. Within each folder, letters are not arranged either alphabetically or chronologically; nor is all the correspondence with a person likely to be grouped together. Some correspondents have not been identified, and some items appear to be misfiled. Note also the topical folders "History," "Ideas," "Israel," and "Tuchman-Biographical;" these contain some notes and drafts as well as correspondence.
    - Arranged alphabetically., 1930, 1957-(1972-1979)
  - Writings/Books: Material gathered into the three following folders
    - U.S. Intelligence: note cards, research material; possibly for The Zimmermann Telegram, undated (Box 1)
    - Notes from China: Original typescript, correspondence, research material, clippings, photographs., 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      General
      (See also letters filed under "China" in correspondence)
    - A Distant Mirror: correspondence, publicity, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Writings/Articles, Reviews, Introductions: A random assortment, 1967-(1972-1979), of typescripts, notes, proof sheets, clippings, reprints, correspondence, and receipts. (Box 1)
  - Writings/Speeches: A random assortment, 1969-1979, of typescripts, notes, clippings, correspondence, and publicity. (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1972-1982; Accession 1983-M-010; 1 linear foot (1 paige box)
  Preliminary inventory by Lynn J. Stewart, 1982 Dec
  Received from: Barbara W. Tuchman via New York Public Library, 1982 Nov 29
  - Correspondence
    - "France 1974", 1974, undated (Box 1)
    - Publication of A Distant Mirror, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
    - A Distant Mirror after publication, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Review of Kissinger's White House Years, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Articles and speeches, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - A Distant Mirror before publication (electrostatic copies, originals at Harvard), 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Articles, speeches and related correspondence
    - Unpublished articles, 1972, undated (Box 1)
    - Notes for speeches, 1973-1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles and speeches, 1975-1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Article: "How to Use a Library", 1980 (Box 1)
    - Speech: "Another Way", 1982 (Box 1)
    - Speech to the Congressional Clearinghouse on the Future, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Speech at Stonybrook, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Mondale, 1981 October (Box 1)
    - UCLA Arms Control, 1982 March (Box 1)
    - I.I.S. Strategic Studies, 1981 (Box 1)
    - "Hazards of a Novia Medievalist", 1975 (Box 1)
    - Speech, Williams: "Citizen & the Military", 1972 June (Box 1)
    - Israel - Vietnam, 1967 June (Box 1)
    - Iphigene, 1981 (Box 1)
    - I.S.S., undated (Box 1)
    - Articles, Op. Ed., NYT: "Defusing the Presidency" (all Watergate and Presidency pieces), 1974 September (Box 1)
    - Speech, Harvard: "History as Mirror", 1973 June (Box 1)
    - Speech, Army War College: "Generalship", 1972 April (Box 1)
    - Speech, Berkeley: "How Will History Judge Us" and Newport, 1974 Apr, 1975 November (Box 1)
    - Articles: "America As Idea", undated (Box 1)
    - "If Mao", 1972 (Box 1)
    - "If Mao"; "Mao to Washington," Foreign Affairs, 1972-1977 (Box 1)
    - Society of Newspaper Editors, 1975 April (Box 1)
    - American Policy in Middle East, undated (Box 1)
    - Gaston Phebus, [1976?] (Box 1)
    - Katonah, 1978 April (Box 1)
    - Montana, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Carter, 1976 June (Box 1)
    - Biography As Prism of History, 1978 November (Box 1)
    - Review: Schama & Friedman, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles: Ladurie & Kissinger, 1979 (Box 1)
    - "The Book", undated (Box 1)
    - Academy Ceremonial, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Jefferson Lecture, 1980 (Box 1)
    - TR at Harvard, 1980 May (Box 1)
    - Putnam and The Past & US, Gr[eenwich], 1979 (Box 1)
    - Historical Newsletter, 1980 January (Box 1)
    - Quality, Times Magazine, 1980 August (Box 1)